Guide to the Center for Columbia River History records circa 1854-2007
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Center for Columbia River History collection
1854-2007
1990-2000
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Coll 292
Center for Columbia River History
10.5 cubic feet 22 document cases and 1 card file box
Research files relating to aspects of the Columbia River Basin, including environmental, social, political, and cultural issues. Files were created by Donna Sinclair and Katrine Barber.
Historical Note
The Center for Columbia River History was created in 1990. It was a consortium of the Washington State Historical Society, Portland State University, and Washington State University, Vancouver, and offered quality history programs about the Columbia River Basin to the general public. It cooperated with other institutions in the Columbia River area to promote research, develop curriculum, teach special courses, publish materials in electronic and text formats, and present public programs about the Basin. Directors of the Center included Katrine Barber and Donna Sinclair.
The collection consists largely of working files of Donna Sinclair, including subject files relating to the Columbia River Basin and its communities. Materials include notes, correspondence, and copies of source materials.
Materials are arranged in four series:
Research Files--Umatilla
Research Files--Cottage Grove
Research Files--Columbia Slough
General research files
The collection is open to the public.
Acquired February 2012, Library Accession 27542
Oral history recordings acquired with this collection have been transferred to the oral history collections of the Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Sinclair, Donna; Barber, Katrine
Center for Columbia River History--Archives
Columbia River; Columbia Slough (Or.); Cottage Grove (Or.); Umatilla County (Or.)
Indians of North America--Oregon; Indians of North America--Washington (State); Human ecology--History--Oregon; Human ecology--History--Washington (State)
Oregon; Washington (State)
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Research Files--Umatilla, circa 1902-2000; undated; Series A
  - 308 Reports, 1943; undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Umatilla Depot, 1996-2000; undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Umatilla Depot Cont., 1994-2000; undated (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Umatilla Depot: Columbia Communities - Umatilla Disaster, 1955-1999; undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Umatilla Working File: Umatilla River Basin, 1946-2000; undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Umatilla Working File: Section V Umatilla Site, Umatilla Today & Tomorrow, 1958-2000; undated (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Umatilla Working File: Community History Biliography CRBP, 2000; undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Umatilla Working File, 1999 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Dept. of Labor Reports, 1988-2000 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Program Manager for Chemical Demilitarization, circa 1998-1999 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Misc. Articles & Other Docs, 1906-1999; undated (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Misc. Articles & Other Docs Cont., 1912-2000; undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Misc. Articles & Other Docs Cont., 1943-2000; undated (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Umatilla Images, 1947-2000; circa 1950s; undated (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Oral History, 1955; 1981 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Primary Docs., 1984-1999; undated (Box-folder 2/6)
  - McNary Dam, 1943 (?); undated (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Population Data, 1999; undated (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Northwest Passage, Journals of Lewis & Clark, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Umatilla Chemical Depot, 1998 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - The Forgotten Tribes, Oral Tales of the Teninos and Adjacent Mid-Columbia River Indian Nations, 1991 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - "Open the Columbia to the Sea" by Lee B. Reeder, 1902 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - McNary Telegram, 1938-1958 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Umatilla Indians, CTUIR, 1999; undated (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Permissions to publish, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Corps Report - McNary & John Day, circa 1971 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Early Communities, Chinese, 1999; undated (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Umatilla Highway Bridge, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Columbia Communities
    - Umatilla Research: Umatilla Maps, 1964-1981; undated (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Umatilla Research: Columbia Communities - Umatilla Working File, circa 1994-1999; undated (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Umatilla Research: Umatilla - Mexican Americans, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Umatilla Research: Umatilla To-Do, 1954-2000 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Umatilla Research--maps, 1942; undated (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Umatilla Photos, 1999; undated (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Umatilla Photos, continued, 1992; 1999 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Dams, 1975; 1999-2000 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Dams: Columbia Communities - Umatilla Dams/Hydro., 1991-1993; undated (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Dams: Section IV - Making Way for Umatilla John Day Site, circa 1948-1999; undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Dams: Section IV - Making Way for Umatilla John Day Site, circa 1958-1999; undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Dams Cont., 1983-1999; undated (Box-folder 4/6)
    - To Add to Umatilla, circa 1952-1998 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Umatilla oral history, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Umatilla Indians, 1957-1999 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Umatilla Indians Cont., 1975-1992 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Umatilla Research, 1956-2000 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Articles, circa 1984-2000 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Colville, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Columbia River Inter-Tribal Fish Commission, 1999 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Cascade Fishery--Paper by Robert C. Dunnell, undated (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Celilo Village Indian Colony, 1999 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Klamath Tribe, 1999 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Kalispel Tribe, 1999 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Nez Perce Tribe, 1999 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Shoshone Bannock, 1990-1999; undated (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Yakama, 1962-2000 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Beckam, Stephen Dow, "Ethnohistorical context of reserved Indian fishing rights: Pacific northwest treaties, 1851-1955" (report for the court case "United States v. Washington"), 1984 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Sohappy Case, undated (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Columbia Communities - River Indians - Wanapum, Native American Research, 1986-1998 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Columbia River Community History, Airport History, St. John's Landfill, 1996; undated (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Misc. Columbia Slough Documents (from black binder), circa 1942-1994; undated (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Misc. Columbia Slough Documents Cont. (from black binder), 1918-1972 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Misc. Columbia Slough Documents Cont. (from black binder), 1953-1996 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Canada, 1993-2000; undated (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Umatilla, 1996-1999; undated (Box-folder 8/2)
  - The Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation, Its Resources & Development Potential, 1976 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, "Training manual for interpreters of McNary Lock and Dam", 1999 January (Box-folder 8/4)
  - McNary articles, circa 1938-1961 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Petticoat council, 1950; undated (Box-folder 8/6)
    Includes papers by Shelly Furtner Wallace, "Umatilla's 'petticoat governemt' 1916-1920"
  - Pendleton Grain Growers, Army Depot, 1998; undated (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Umatilla, Columbia Slough, Cottage Grove--oral history questions, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Dam breaching, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 8/9)
  - Dam breaching--Umatilla, Salmon, 1999 (Box-folder 8/10)
- Research Files--Cottage Grove, 1854-2000; Series B
  - Cottage Grove Forestry, circa 1909; 1970-2000; undated (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Cottage Grove Forestry Cont., circa 1913-1999 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Dorena and Cottage Grove Dams, 1935-1997; undated (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Primary Materials/Images Permissions CG, 1999-2000; undated (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Cottage Grove Images, 1898-1999; undated (Box-folder 9/5)
  - CG Flood Events, 1941; 1970; undated (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Bohemia Mining, 1893-1970; undated (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Bibliographies, 1986; 1994; undated (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Misc. documents, 1854-1996 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Cottage Grove documents, 1884-1999 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Narrators (oral histories), 1999-2000 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Willamette River today, circa 1969-1999 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - All-American city, undated (Box-folder 10/5)
- Research Files--Columbia Slough, 1870-2000; Series C
  - Maps/General Info., 1974-2000; undated (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Maps/General Info. Cont., 1979-2000; undated (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Swindell Material--United States, Office of Indian Affairs, Division of Forestry and Grazing, "Report on source nature and extent of the fishing, hunting and miscellaneous related rights of certain Indian tribes in Washington and Oregon together with affidavits showing locations of a number of usual and accustomed fishing grounds and stations", 1942 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Spokane Indians, 1999 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Burns Paiute, 1997-1999; undated (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Warm Springs - Oral History Project, 1999-2000; undated (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Corps Feasibility Study, 1999 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Misc. Documents, 1964-2000 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Slough Permissions: Slough - Images/Permiss. Docs., 1999-2001 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Slough Permissions: Oral History Permissions, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Slough Permissions: Columbia Slough - Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Slough Permissions: Columbia Slough - generaly info. & project descriptions, undated (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Slough Permissions: Oregonian Permissions, circa 1942-2001 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Portland International Airport, 1933-2009; undated (Box-folder 12/6)
  - Columbia Slough Task Force, circa 1972 (Box-folder 12/7)
  - Columbia Slough Closure, 1870; 1997 (Box-folder 12/8)
  - Columbia Slough Closure, 1968, 1969-1987; undated (Box-folder 12/9)
  - Columbia Slough Closure - North Portland Peninsula Study, 1972 (Box-folder 12/10)
  - MDD #1 Scrapbook, 1948-1993; undated (Box-folder 12/11)
  - Our place: environmental community, Roosevelt High School, 2002 (Box-folder 12/12)
  - Kenton, 1995-2000; undated (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Neighbors Between the Rivers, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Slough-Enviro: Slough - Pollution, 1971-2000 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Slough-Enviro: Misc., 1995-2000 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - Slough-Enviro: Fishing on the Slough, 1994-1997; undated (Box-folder 13/5)
  - Slough-Enviro: Slough - CSO's, 1970-1997 (Box-folder 13/6)
  - Slough-Enviro: Col. Slough - Water Quality, 1959-2000; undated (Box-folder 13/7)
  - Slough-Enviro: Columbia Slough - Recreation (PIR) (Golf Courses), 1972-2000; undated (Box-folder 13/8)
  - Slough Communities
    - Columbia Slough Oral History Class, Geoff Weherell paper, 2000 (Box-folder 14/1)
    - Hayden Island/Bridgeton, 1984-1999 (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Commercial Communities, 1988-1998 (Box-folder 14/3)
    - Vanport, circa 1942-1990 (Box-folder 14/4)
    - St. Johns Neighborhood, 1909-2000 (Box-folder 14/5)
    - St. Johns Landfill, circa 1971-2000 (Box-folder 14/6)
    - Whitaker Panels, circa 1994-2000 (Box-folder 14/7)
    - Portland Neighborhoods, 1999 (Box-folder 14/8)
    - Japanese Americans, 1980-1999 (Box-folder 14/9)
    - Japanese in Oregon, 1995-1997; undated (Box-folder 14/10)
    - Rivergate, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 14/11)
  - Jantzen Beach Center, 1927-1999 (Box-folder 14/12)
  - Hayden Island, 1903-2000 (Box-folder 14/13)
  - Port of Portland, 1972 (Box-folder 14/14)
  - Swan Island, 1976 (Box-folder 14/15)
  - Columbia Slough Trail Project, 1903-1996 (Box-folder 14/16)
  - Slough Organizations: Smith & Bybee Lakes, Audobon, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 14/17)
  - Slough Organizations: Friends of Blue & Fairview Lake, circa 1992-1999 (Box-folder 14/18)
  - Slough Organizations: Northwest Environmental Advocates, Willamette Riverkeepers, undated (Box-folder 14/19)
  - Slough Organizations: Columbia Slough Watershed Council, 1999; undated (Box-folder 14/20)
  - Oregon Historical Society oral histories, 2000 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - CCRH Web Misc., circa 1998-2000 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - CCRH Web: Columbia River Basin Project - Donna [Sinclair], circa 1997-1999 (Box-folder 15/3)
  - Community Hist. - Slough To-Do, crica 1972-2000 (Box-folder 15/4)
  - Maps: Columbia Slough Maps, crica 1915-2999 (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Maps: Basin Maps, undated (Box-folder 15/6)
  - Maps: Misc., 1944 (Box-folder 15/7)
  - Slough - photos, circa 1998-2000 (Box-folder 15/8)
  - Slough - photos, 1988-2000; undated (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Slough oral histories, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 16/2)
  - Slough Oral Hist.: Columbia Slough - Helen Miles, 2000 (Box-folder 16/3)
  - Slough - Primary Docs.: Misc., 1948-2000 (Box-folder 16/4)
  - Slough - Primary Docs.: Columbia Slough - BES, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 16/5)
  - Slough - Primary Docs.: Scanned Documents, Columbia Slough, 1946-1995; undated (Box-folder 16/6)
  - Research - Slough: Research info. - Slough, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 16/7)
  - Research - Slough: Slough articles, circa 1972-1997 (Box-folder 16/8)
  - Research - Slough: Misc. research materials, 1945-1998 (Box-folder 16/9)
  - Columbia River Slough--Research notebook (Donna Sinclair?), undated (Box-folder 16/10)
  - Slough capstones (Portland State University student projects), 1993-2000 (Box-folder 16/11)
  - Planning Goals, 1997-1999; undated (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Erosion & Sedimentation, 1997; 1999 (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Columbia South Shore, 1997-2000; undated (Box-folder 17/3)
  - Floods, 1970-1996; undated (Box-folder 17/4)
  - Albina, 1945-1970; 1993 (Box-folder 17/5)
  - Maps, undated (Box-folder 17/6)
- General Files, 1945-2007; Series D
  - OHS Oral Histories
    - Bernard Foster: OHS Oral History, 2004 (Box-folder 18/1)
    - Bobbie Foster: OHS Oral History, 1999 (Box-folder 18/2)
    - Mark Hatfield: OHS Oral History, 1998 (Box-folder 18/3)
    - Malcolm Marsh: An Oral History, 2007 (Box-folder 18/4)
    - Robert E. Jones: An Oral History, 2007 (Box-folder 18/5)
    - Randall Kester: An Oral History, 2006 (Box-folder 18/6)
  - Dissenters
    - American Rivers, 1999 (Box-folder 19/1)
    - Bonneville Power Administration, 1999 (Box-folder 19/2)
    - Christian Enviro Groups, 1999 (Box-folder 19/3)
  - Breaching Dams, 1991-1999 (Box-folder 19/4)
  - Columbia River History, circa 1995-2000 (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Vanport Flood--Microfilm from Multnomah County Sherrif's Office "Flood property thru slavaged autos.", circa 1946-1948 (Box-folder 19/6)
    Original color slides depicting damage from the 1948 flood in Portland have been separated to Org. Lot 1218, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
  - Columbia R. - method, circa 1984-1998 (Box-folder 19/7)
  - Columbia River Alliance, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 19/8)
  - Columbia River Basin and Estuary--Report by Angus Duncan, et. al., "Overhaul of maintenance: a review of existing and proposed governance institutions in the Columbia River Basin and Estuary.", 1999 January (Box-folder 19/9)
  - Columbia River United, 1999 (Box-folder 19/10)
  - Columbia and Snake Rivers Campaign, 1999 (Box-folder 19/11)
  - CRITFC ISSUES (FOR CIARIC), 1996-2000 (Box-folder 19/12)
  - Current Issues, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 19/13)
  - Current Issues--Clippings, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 19/14-19/15)
  - Current Issues--Clippings, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Dams - Breaching, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Dams - History, 1977-1998; undated (Box-folder 20/3)
    Includes: "Presentation for the Oregon Historical Society," by Katrine Barber, 1998 May 16; "The Dalles Dam: the death of Celilo Falls and a native culture," by Cathy Alzner, 1995 June 7.
  - E. Oregon Trip, 2000 May (Box-folder 20/4)
  - Endangerd Species Act, National Maritime Fisheries Service, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 20/5)
  - Endangerd Species Act, National Maritime Fisheries Service, Federal Energy Regulation Commission, 1993-2000 (Box-folder 20/6)
  - Ferries project, 2002 (Box-folder 20/7)
  - Fish/CCRH, 1976-1999 (Box-folder 20/8)
  - Fish - Idaho Statesman, 1968-1998 (Box-folder 20/9)
  - Friends of Columbia Gorge, 1999 (Box-folder 21/1)
  - Hanford - CCRH, 1989-1999 (Box-folder 21/2)
  - Hanford Reach, 1999 (Box-folder 21/3)
  - Harvest, 1998 (Box-folder 21/4)
  - Hells Canyon CCRH, 1970 (Box-folder 21/6)
  - Hatcheries, 1998 (Box-folder 21/5)
  - General Outline of subjects (Managing the Columbia River oral history project), undated (Box-folder 21/7)
  - General River Management, 1976-1999 (Box-folder 21/8)
  - Grand Coulee Dam, 1958; 1971 (Box-folder 21/9)
  - Grazing--magazines, 1993 (Box-folder 21/10)
  - Idaho - General pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 21/11)
  - Idaho Politics, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 21/12)
  - Idaho Rivers United, 1995-1998; undated (Box-folder 21/13)
  - Interior Columbia Basin Ecosystem Mgmt., 1998-1999 (Box-folder 21/14)
  - Irrigation, 1978; 1998-1999 (Box-folder 21/15)
  - Koberstein Articles, 1999 (Box-folder 21/16)
  - Lewis & Clark Conference, 2000 (Box-folder 21/17)
  - Names of Resources and Potential IVs, CCRH, 1949-2000 (Box-folder 21/18)
  - Native Americans, circa 1998-2000 (Box-folder 21/19)
  - Native American Fishing Rights, 1999 (Box-folder 21/20)
  - New CCRH Articles, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 21/21)
  - Nuclear (issue of the Boise weekly), 1998 May 7-13 (Box-folder 21/22)
  - Umatilla, Oregon Oral History Project, 1999-2000, 1983-2000 (Box-folder 21/23)
  - Pollution, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 21/24)
  - Research (the Orange Folder), circa 1999-2000 (Box-folder 22/1)
  - Power Issues ("That Dam File"), 1945-2000 (Box-folder 22/2-22/3)
  - Publications Addressing Salmon Crisis, 1997; 2000 (Box-folder 22/4)
  - River Network, circa 1998-2000 (Box-folder 22/5)
  - Salmon Recovery - general, circa 1998-2000 (Box-folder 22/6)
  - Save Our Wild Salmon, 1999 (Box-folder 22/7)
  - Treaties - General, 1999-2000; undated (Box-folder 22/8)
  - Tribes, 1996-1999; undated (Box-folder 22/9)
    Includes papers by Cain Allen, "They called it progress: water development projects and the marginalization of Native Americans on the Columbia."
  - Trojan, 1971-1991 (Box-folder 22/10)
  - Umatilla Reservation - general, 1993-2000 (Box-folder 22/11)
  - Water Policy--"Ecosystem values and governance in western river basins: a commentary and proposal," Angus Duncan, 1997 May 15 (Box-folder 22/12)
  - Watersheds-- History, science, the law, and watershed recovery in the GrandeRonde: a case study by Angus Duncan, published by Sea Grant, 1998 (Box-folder 22/13)
  - Wild salmon forever: a citizens' strategy to restore northwest salmon and watersheds, Save Our Wild Salmon Coalition, undated (Box-folder 22/14)
  - Willamette River (article by Bill Monroe), 2001 (Box-folder 22/15)
  - Computer diskettes, circa 1999-2000 (Box-folder CFB-1)